To get full marks
on a short
answer question, or SAQ,
you really
only need to do two things.
Understand what you are being
asked to write about and
write it using the
three-part
formula.
Simpler than simple.
But for
many AP
World, AP Euro, and APUSH students, SAQ is
not "simpler than
simple."  Rather,
why does this supposedly simple
thing make my armpits
sweat, my insides
clench, cause me
a fair amount of
existential dread,
and make me question
all of my life
choices?
Just like a lemon.
But look, it doesn't have to
be
that hard.  You just
need someone to
explain everything properly.
And so, I am here for exactly
that.
If you're ready
to rack your brains,
well, let's get started.  Oh, and
be sure to
watch until the end,
because I have to tell you
how my previous
advice on the SAQ
completely changed
after what
happened this year
during the
national exam assessment
.  First, let's
dive in and
understand what we're
dealing with.
Short
answer questions for APUSH, AP
World, or AP Euro—by the way,
they are all scored
the same, so everything
I say now
applies to each of
them.
Short answer questions
can be divided into
two types.  The first
contains a stimulus, which
will be a document to
read or
an image to
analyze.  It is followed by
three tasks,
labeled A, B, C. And the
second type has no
stimulus and contains
only three tasks.  For
each task, you
get either one
point or zero, and
no middle
ground.  Sometimes they
add a
two-point assignment
, but that's only if
you're asked to
do two things.
So, on the AP exam in
May, you will be given
four such SAQs, and you
must answer
three of them.  Your
answers don't have to
be essays, they should
be about
two or three complete
sentences, and I'll
tell you exactly what I
recommend soon.  So, the
first step:
understand the incentive and the
task.  The first thing
you need to do
to answer the SAQ
is to understand the stimulus
and the task itself.  I
highly
recommend
marking these
tasks because,
repeat after me:
under pressure, you are dumber
than you think.
So, where should you
start?  Well,
you'll want to start by
reading or
looking at the stimulus.
If you feel like it,
I advise you to open your
palm, wet it, and
slap yourself.  This is
not where you should
start.  Start by
reading the questions, and
here's why.  You don't have much
time to answer, and
if you start by
analyzing the stimulus, you'll
just waste time
because you won't even
know what to look for.
So start by
reading the three
questions, mark them
, and only then
move on to
the stimulus when
you know exactly what
to look for in it.  So, what
exactly should be indicated in
questions?  Well, three
things.  The first is
the category or
categories
you are asked to write about.
The second is the time
period you
need to write about.  And
the third is the skill of
historical thinking
, which should
structure your
answer.  Here, for
example, is the first
short answer question (SAQ)
from the 2022 AP World exam.
First, select a
category.  Here you
are asked to talk
about economic
development, and here about
political development.  This is extremely
important, because if your
answer does not
fit into these
categories, you will
not receive points.
Second, indicate the
time period.  If
your answer
goes beyond these
years, then no matter how
brilliant it is
, you will not
receive points.  And third,
mark the skill of
historical thinking
.  In this case, you
see the expression "
led to", and this is a
question about cause and
effect.
This means that
any evidence in your
answer must
point to
causality.  Okay,
now that you
understand the task,
you can move on to the
incentive, if there is one.
Look at it and
highlight what will
help you
answer the
question.  Now
let's move on to how to
respond.
Everyone has their
favorite acronym
for answering SAQs,
but in my opinion, the
best one is T E A T:
topic sentence,
explanation of evidence, and
analysis.  Let me
explain.  Your
topic sentence
is a single statement
that essentially
rephrases the important
parts of the question and
cites specific
evidence.  This is important not
because it gives you
points, but because it
helps you stay
on topic, which is what
you will actually
get points for.
Consider this
question from the
2022 AP Euro exam.  Describe
one significant
cultural or
intellectual change
during the Renaissance.
My topic
sentence would be like this
.  One of the significant
intellectual changes
during the Renaissance was the
emphasis on humanism.
So, you see, I
rephrased the important
parts of the question
to stay on topic and
cited evidence that
demonstrates the change.
The second part is
an explanation of my
evidence, which essentially
means giving a
definition.  So, my
version would look
something like this.
Humanism described the
Renaissance belief in the
unlimited
potential of man as an end in
itself.  If you've
done these two things, you're
probably
happy with yourself, but
you need to take
another step and
analyze this
evidence.  This means that
you must show
how your evidence
supports the
topic sentence.
Now look
carefully.  I'm talking about the
intellectual changes
during the Renaissance,
I called it
humanism and gave it a
definition.  I named
the change, but I didn't show
how it happened, and
that's important.  So my
third sentence would be this
.  Before the
Renaissance, the dominant
view of human
potential was
limited by the widespread
belief in the doctrine of
original sin.
However, thanks to the
pioneering work of
Petrarch and other
humanists during the
Renaissance, a
new
confidence in
human potential began to emerge
.  These three sentences
will earn you a point.
You might now
object that this is
too much to
discuss.  Gow, ca
n't it be
easier?  If you
had asked me a year
ago, I would have said
yes, it could be easier,
but today I would say
no, and let me
explain why.  You
may have noticed that
you keep
coming up with three
main
task verbs.  These are:
define, describe and
explain.  I was always
taught that for the
"define" task, it's
enough to write a
topic sentence, and that's it
.  So for this
assignment, I would advise
you to write: One
of the economic
factors that led
to the situation on the map
was the forced
free trade agreements
between Britain and
China after the
Opium War.    They
just defined
economic development
, and that's it.  But I
no longer advise
doing that, and here's why.
Although the College Board itself
explained what
“determine” means
in its course
and exam description, and my
answer is at
that level, this
year on the national
AP World test,
no points were awarded unless you
explained the evidence.  This is
just madness.
As far as I
know, this has
only happened on the AP
World test, but if it's
possible there, it could
happen in other
subjects.  So my
advice: apply the
T structure to every
answer.  This way you will
never be fooled by
AP leaders who
don't even
follow their own
standards.  Okay,
if you need
more help
writing your
AP History papers, click
here and get my
AP Essay Writing Crash Course.  And here
I have many more videos
about writing
texts that
will help you with
all your other essays.  So,
see you later.  I am
Lawrence.